You may not realize this,
ربما لا تدركون هذا،
but there are more bacteria in your body than stars in our entire galaxy.
لكن هناك بكتيريا في أجسامكم أكثر من عدد النجوم في مجرتنا بأكملها.
This fascinating universe of bacteria inside of us
إن العالم الساحر من البكتيريا بداخلنا
is an integral part of our health,
هو جزء لا يتجزأ من صحتنا،
and our technology is evolving so rapidly
وإن تقنيتنا تتطور بسرعة شديدة
that today we can program these bacteria like we program computers.
حتى أن بإمكاننا اليوم برمجة هذه البكتيريا كما نبرمج الحواسيب.
Now, the diagram that you see here,
الآن، المخطط الذي ترونه هنا،
I know it looks like some kind of sports play,
أعلم أنه يبدو كنوع ما من الألعاب الرياضية،
but it is actually a blueprint of the first bacterial program I developed.
ولكنه في الحقيقة مخطط لأول برنامج بكتيري قمت بتطويره.
And like writing software, we can print and write DNA
وكما هو الحال في كتابة برنامج، فإن بإمكاننا طباعة وكتابة الحمض النووي
into different algorithms and programs inside of bacteria.
بألغوريثمات وبرامج مختلفة داخل البكتيريا.
What this program does is produces fluorescent proteins
ما يفعله هذا البرنامج هو إنتاج بروتينات فلورية
in a rhythmic fashion
بنمط متواتر
and generates a small molecule
وتوليد جزيء صغير
that allows bacteria to communicate and synchronize,
يسمح للبكتيريا بالتواصل والتزامن،
as you're seeing in this movie.
كما ترون في هذا الفيلم.
The growing colony of bacteria that you see here
المستعمرة البكتيرية المتنامية التي ترونها هنا
is about the width of a human hair.
هي عن عرض شعر الإنسان.
Now, what you can't see is that our genetic program
الآن، ما لا تستطيعون رؤيته هو أن برنامجنا الجيني
instructs these bacteria to each produce small molecules,
يوجه كل واحدة من هذه البكتيريا إلى إنتاج جزيئات صغيرة،
and these molecules travel between the thousands of individual bacteria
وتنتقل هذه الجزيئات بين آلاف الكائنات البكتيرية
telling them when to turn on and off.
وتخبرها متى تعمل ومتى تتوقف عن العمل.
And the bacteria synchronize quite well at this scale,
وتتزامن البكتيريا جيدًا على هذا النطاق،
but because the molecule that synchronizes them together can only travel so fast,
ولكن لأن الجزيء الذي يزامنها معًا يستطيع فقط الحركة بسرعة كبيرة،
in larger colonies of bacteria, this results in traveling waves
ففي المستعمرات البكتيرية الأكبر، يسبب هذا موجات حركية
between bacteria that are far away from each other,
بين البكتيريا المتباعدة عن بعضها البعض،
and you can see these waves going from right to left across the screen.
وبإمكانكم رؤية هذه الموجات تنطلق من جهة اليمين إلى يسار الشاشة.
Now, our genetic program relies on a natural phenomenon
يعتمد برنامجنا الجيني على ظاهرة طبيعية
called quorum sensing,
تدعى استشعار النصاب،
in which bacteria trigger coordinated and sometimes virulent behaviors
وفيها تطلق البكتيريا سلوكيات متناسقة وأحيانًا سامة
once they reach a critical density.
عندما تصل إلى كثافة حرجة.
You can observe quorum sensing in action in this movie,
تستطيعون في هذا الفيلم ملاحظة استشعار النصاب أثناء عمله،
once it reaches a high or critical density.
عندما تصل إلى كثافة حرجة أو عالية.
Our genetic program
يستمر برنامجنا الجيني
as the colony grows outwards.
بينما تتمد المستعمرة إلى الخارج.
This particular movie and experiment we call The Supernova,
هذه التجربة وهذا الفيلم بالتحديد ندعوه المستعر الأعظم،
because it looks like an exploding star.
لأنها تبدو كنجم متفجر.
Now, besides programming these beautiful patterns,
الآن، إلى جانب برمجة هذه القوالب الجميلة،
I wondered, what else can we get these bacteria to do?
تساءلتُ، ما الذي يمكننا إجبار البكتيريا على فعله أيضًا؟
And I decided to explore how we can program bacteria
وقررت استكشاف كيفية برمجة البكتيريا
to detect and treat diseases in our bodies like cancer.
لكشف ومعالجة الأمراض بأجسامنا كالسرطان.
One of the surprising facts about bacteria
أحد الحقائق المدهشة بشأن البكتيريا
is that they can naturally grow inside of tumors.
هي أنها تستطيع أن تنمو بشكل طبيعي داخل أورامنا.
This happens because typically tumors
هذا يحدث لأن الأورام نموذجيًا
are areas where the immune system has no access,
هي مناطق ليس لنظام المناعة دخل فيها،
and so bacteria find these tumors
ولذا تجد البكتيريا هذه الأورام
and use them as a safe haven to grow and thrive.
وتستخدمها كملاذ آمن لتنمو وتزدهر.
We started using probiotic bacteria
بدأنا باستخدام متممات غذائية بكتيرية
which are safe bacteria that have a health benefit,
وهي بكتيريا آمنة لديها فوائد صحية،
and found that when orally delivered to mice,
ووجدنا بأنها عند إيصالها عن طريق الفم إلى فأر،
these probiotics would selectively grow inside of liver tumors.
هذه المتممات البكتيرية ستنمو انتقائيًا داخل الأورام الحية.
We realized that the most convenient way
أدركنا أن أكثر طريقة ملائمة
to highlight the presence of the probiotics,
لإبراز تواجد المتممات الغذائية،
and hence, the presence of the tumors,
وبالتالي، تواجد الأورام،
was to get these bacteria to produce a signal
أن نجعل هذه البكتيريا تنتج إشارة
that would be detectable in the urine,
ستكون قابلة للكشف من خلال البول،
and so we specifically programmed these probiotics
لذا برمجنا هذه المتممات تحديدًا
to make a molecule that would change the color of your urine
لإنشاء جزيء سيغير من لون البول خاصتك
to indicate the presence of cancer.
للإشارة إلى وجود السرطان.
We went on to show that this technology
وأكملنا العمل لإظهار أن هذه التقنية
could sensitively and specifically detect liver cancer,
بإمكانها حسيًا وتحديدًا الكشف عن سرطان الكبد،
one that is challenging to detect otherwise.
وهو سرطان يصعب كشفه بالطرق الأخرى.
Now, since these bacteria specifically localize to tumors,
الآن، لأن هذه البكتيريا تتمركز في الأورام،
we've been programming them to not only detect cancer
فقد كنا نبرمجها ليس فقط لكشف السرطان
but also to treat cancer
بل أيضًا لعلاجه
by producing therapeutic molecules from within the tumor environment
عن طريق إنتاج جزيئات علاجية من داخل بيئة الورم
that shrink the existing tumors,
تقوم بتقليص الأورام الموجودة،
and we've been doing this using quorum sensing programs
وقد كنا نفعل هذا باستخدام برامج استشعار النصاب
like you saw in the previous movies.
كالتي رأيتموها في الأفلام السابقة.
Altogether, imagine in the future taking a programmed probiotic
وبوجه عام، تخيلوا الحديث مستقبلًا عن متممات غذائية بكتيرية مبرمجة
that could detect and treat cancer,
باستطاعتها كشف وعلاج السرطان،
or even other diseases.
أو حتى أمراض أخرى.
Our ability to program bacteria
إن قدرتنا على برمجة البكتيريا
and program life
وبرمجة الحياة
opens up new horizons in cancer research,
تفتح آفاقًا جديدة في أبحاث السرطان،
and to share this vision, I worked with artist Vik Muniz
ومن أجل مشاركة هذه الرؤية، عملت مع الفنان فيك مونيز
to create the symbol of the universe,
لإنشاء شعار العالم،
made entirely out of bacteria or cancer cells.
الذي تم صنعه بالكامل من البكتيريا والخلايا السرطانية.
Ultimately, my hope is that the beauty and purpose of this microscopic universe
وفي النهاية، أملي هو أن يستطيع جمال وهدف هذا العالم الميكروبي
can inspire new and creative approaches for the future of cancer research.
إلهام مناهج جديدة وإبداعية من أجل مستقبل البحث في مجال السرطان.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)